Nicholas G. McMullen

Certified Compensation & Human Resources Professional email: nicholasgmcmullen@gmail.com | web: https://nickmcmullen.github.io social: https://www.linkedin.com/in/nicholas-mcmullen/

Summary

Analytically-inclined, people-oriented HR practitioner with experience supporting executives and front-line teams as a strategic partner. Skilled in compensation design and management, people analytics, human resources operations, and onboarding. Experience implementing, integrating, and managing a variety of HR technology solutions, architecting compensation programs, and leading people-people teams.

Employment

Compensation and People Analytics Lead

January 2022 - Present

RStudio PBC

Boston, MA, USA

- Lead all aspects of RStudio's compensation operations, administration, and design including base salary, short-term incentive (STI), long-term incentive (LTI)
- Assist in the analysis and design of executive compensation programs and incentives
- Participate in salary surveys, benchmark jobs to align with compensation philosophy
- Manage cadenced departmental compensation reviews with executives
- Approve compensation for all external job offers, promotions, and internal transfers
- Build, automate dashboards using R/RStudio/shiny to provide automated, people-related insights to executives
- Configure HR systems to meet company needs and liaise with IT to ensure accurate, secure transfer of data between systems

People Operations Partner

January 2021 - January 2022

RStudio PBC

Boston, MA, USA

- Built career framework and aligned to salary structures for engineering department
- Conducted job analysis and market pricing of all company jobs
- Assisted in the implementation and company-wide rollout of new HRIS
- Acted as the initial point of contact for employee relations issues
- Trained and coached small groups of managers on effective management practices

Senior Specialist Total Rewards Content

September 2020 - January 2021

WorldatWork

Scottsdale, AZ, USA

- Delivered a preliminary People Analytics practice strategy to association leadership
- Conducted competitive market research in the people analytics education market
- Advised practice leaders on trends, opportunities, and threats in total rewards

Manager People Systems and Analytics

January 2020 - September 2020

Alliance Residential Company

Phoenix, AZ, USA

- Oversaw operation of all human resources information systems including HRIS (UltiPro), ATS (iCIMS), Compensation (Salary.com), and LMS (Fuse LXP)
- Led implementation of new organizational corporate social responsibility platform
- Conducted job analysis and evaluation of all company jobs
- Administered Quarterly Incentive Program, including building code-based distribution and audit capabilities
- Evaluated effectiveness of HR programs and field performance using R and RStudio and presented findings to executives

Manager Talent Analytics and Operations

May 2018 - January 2020

Alliance Residential Company

Phoenix, AZ, USA

- Oversaw operation of human resources information systems including ATS (iCIMS), Compensation (Salary.com), and LMS (Cornerstone OnDemand & Fuse LXP)
- Led implementation of Fuse LXP and company-wide conversion from Cornerstone OnDemand LMS
- Managed Talent Coordinator team responsible for pre-hire onboarding tasks and workflows including offer letters, compliance, and gueuing profiles for import to HRIS
- Automated recruiting billback process, including integrating data sources from CRM, ATS, and HRIS and utilizing open source R tools, saving 30+ hours of manual work per month
- Developed suite of automated Tableau dashboards to support monthly reporting needs of Talent executive team

Learning and Development Intern

June 2017 - August 2017

Alliance Residential Company

Phoenix, AZ, USA

- Assisted with administration and management of Cornerstone OnDemand LMS
- Built and distributed reports required by the field Learning and Development team
- Analyzed training program data for business impact and presented results to executive team

Education

B.A. magna cum laude, Applied Mathematics and Statistics

August 2014 - May 2018

Macalester College St. Paul, MN, USA

Certifications

Certified Compensation Professional (CCP)

Expires November 2024

WorldatWork

Global Remuneration Professional (GRP)

Expires November 2024

WorldatWork

Professional in Human Resources (PHR)

Expires February 2024

Human Resources Certification Institute (HRCI)

Tableau Desktop 2019 Certified Associate (expired)

Expires October 2021

Tableau Software

Skills

Base pay design and administration

- Job analysis, documentation, and evaluation
- Incentive compensation program management
- HRIS integration and administration
- ATS implementation, administration
- LMS implementation, administration
- Talent onboarding process development and management
- People program analysis and evaluation
- Data cleaning and manipulation
- Process improvement, design, and automation
- People team management

Software Experience

- R programming
- Shiny app development
- RStudio IDE
- BambooHR HRIS
- Greenhouse.io ATS
- Culture Amp
- Salary.com CompAnalyst
- UltiPro HRIS (UKG)
- iCIMS ATS
- Fuse LXP
- Cornerstone OnDemand LMS
- Qualtrics